Another competitor
又来一个扩包碗的
Okay, let's start practicing
好 我们练功
Come on, ready...
好 来 准备
One. . -
一一
Two. . -
一
Sir, a Master Liu is looking for you
少蓄 外面有位廖师传找你
May I Know who you are?
壳位是
I'm the patriarch of the Liu Fist Sect
我是碎家拳的掌阁人
I just started a martial club in Fo Shan
刚刚在佛山成立一家武馆
I hear that Master Ip is a Wing Chun expert
我聘襄革上师傅熏得一手好访春源
I'd love to practice with you today
所以今天特地找你来切磋一下
Can we do it some other day?
改天吧 好不好
It's not convenient right now
你来得不是时候啊
Since I'm already here,
反正我已经来了
let's just play around for a bit
玩玩而已 用不了多长时间
It's all private. No one else shall Know who wins
咱们是闭站切磋 输赢洛有人知道
It's not a matter of winning. I'm having dinner
不是输赢的问题 是我在吃包呀
In that case... I'1]1 wait for you
那 我等你
Master Liu
廖上师傅
Have you eaten yet?
吃过马洛有
Please join me
来一起吃啊
You want one?
抽粳叶
No, thanks
不客所
Is the food all right tonight?
今隐的饭菜还可以鄙
Very good indeed
好 好
That's good
那就好了
Very quick
好快
Leave it, Uncle Wang. Close the door first
旺叔 别收拾了 先关门
Master Liu
廖上师傅
Please!
=主 ]
Are you okay?
没事吧
I'm fine...
没事 没事
Let's start again!
绸来
Okay. here I come
那我再来了
Touche!
中
All touche!
全中
Thanks for being lenient. Master Liu
承太了 廖师传
Thanks for teaching me. I've learnt a lot
多谢赐教 欧益恨多
The pleasure was all mine
彼此彼此
Regarding this private duel, Master Ip...
各次闭门比武的事 药师傅你
I won't tell anyone. Don't worry
绝对不会透漏 放心吧
Thanks so much. I'm totally grateful
感激不尾 感激不妨
Goodbye
告静
Farewel]
请慢走
So long
不和送了
With “Move 1000 Catties with 4 Taels”
革问一招天王托塔 再来一个四两斤干斤
Ip pushed Master Liu's whole body away
就把廖师傅整个震开了
Isn't “Move 1000 Catties with 4 Taels” Tai Chi?
四两斤干斤 不是太极拳的哮
I thought Master Ip practiced Wing Chun
我聘襄革上师傅熏访春的呀 是不是啊
Anyway. he pushed him away with one hand
纺之就是一手将他推开了
Liu refused to admit defeat
廖师傅还不服输
Ip kept chasing after him fiercely!
然后革辕 就很癌很党的追鞭他打呀
But Liu remained indignant after being hit
不过 庆师傅中招之短 还是深深不釜
He jumped at Ip like a hungry dog
竟然用试狗护食来打革半
These tea leaves are pretty good and cheap
过种茶革不错的 很便宜
Thank you Got to go
请慢走
Goodbye Goodbye. see you next time
再见 下次再来
Who put these here, Uncle Ping?
平权 各个是谁放在二的
Your brother
是你弟弟扬的
I thought Liu was good but he's so bad at defence
我原以为大师傅功夫好 可志还册之力都泊有
and was beaten up like a pighead
被打得像猪头一柑
He co-owns his dad's restaurant. He's always idle
老区的酒樱他也有份 整天在那复手好问
Ask that kid to serve the customers
叫那兔患子赶紧遏来招呼客人
Good morning
早啊
Brother Ip!
问哥
Is Quan here yet?
泉哥来了唉
He's waiting for you upstairs
在上面等你呢
Been here long. Quan?
阿录 等了很久了
You're always late
你每次都脖到
I'm busy
忙嘛
Busy with what?
忙什么呀
Drinking tea, eating. practicing
还不是喝茶 吃饭 和练功夫
What else?
还有什感可忙的
This tea smells nice
各茶挺理的
I'm talking about you
我在襄你呀
Have you ordered yet?
叫东西吃了叶
I got something to discuss with you
有事跟你商量
Let's eat first and then we'll talk
先吃了再慢慢褒
This just came out of the oven! Try it...
新出类的 噶喧…了吻一下
Heard that you had a duel with Master Liu
对他们褒你跟碎师傅切磋
and had beaten him quickly. Is that true?
还很快就把他打赢了 是不是真的
Who told you that, Lin?
哪个底的 武痢林
My brother
我弟弟襄的
Should've told me earlier. I'm his disciple now!
你们切磋早点告诉我嘛 我还拜他为师呢
But you've been a disciple of every master
你哪个师傅都拜的嘛
Was the duel private. Brother Ip?
问哥 你们是不是闭门切磋
We have things to discuss. Leave us for now
我们有事商量 你先出去吧
Then I won't disturb your private conversation
那我不妨破你们闭门谈事
Morning. Master! Morning
师傅早 早
Master
师傅
Heard that you were beaten by Ip Man
有人襄你被某问打败了
Everyone in Fo Shan Knows about it now
现在全佛山的人都知道了
Nonsense! Who told you that?
胡襄 谁襄的
Yuan at the restaurant
茶楼的沙脆源
Everything is costly in Fo Shan these days
佛山现在物价袜了
So what?
那又怎样
That means the economy is good in Fo Shan
那就是说呢 佛山经济好了
Everybody can afford to spend money
各个都有钱花
Is that so?
是哮
Clothing is the most important in our daily lives
你想想 衣食住行衣为先
There will be lots of demand for future clothing
将来的服廓量 供应需求一定很大
I‘11 open a cotton mill to provide cotton for them
所以我想开个棉花厂 提供棉料给他们
I want you to be my partner
我想跟你合股
I don't Know anything about business
我不庆合做生意的
But I do
我庆合就行了
I'm not in need of money
我又不缺钱
Who's Yuan? Show yourself !
谁是沙脆源 给我滚出来
I am
我是
You rascal. You ruined my reputation
是你在茶楼胡襄八道 毁坏我韦汉
Master...
师傅
I must teach you a lesson! Master---
我今天要教训你 师传 师傅
He's my brother. Let's talk
他是我弟弟 有事慢慢褒
Calm down. Okay. Master?
不要生氟好不好 师傅
Your brother?
你弟弟
He ruined my reputation
你弟弟胡襄八道 毁坏我的韦崇
He said I was beaten by Ip Man
褒我被革半打败了
What's gonna happen to my martial club?
过尽我今生 渤怎床在武馆街立足
Who will want to be my disciples?
我还怎友开馆收徒弟
Apologize!
师传 还不道委
I didn't do anything wrong. I told the truth!
我哪有错 我襄事实了嘛
You're bullshitting again! You-:-
你在胡褒八道
Master...
师傅…
Master Ip is upstairs. Seek him out if you have guts!
革问就在上面 有种上去找他
What? Go!
怎奈样 走啊
Take it easy. Master...
师傅 消消氟 消消氟
Master--- Don't be angry. Master
师传 师傅 你别生气呀 师傅
I've been wronged. Master Ip
革师傅 我被人宪枉啊
Master...
师传 师傅
Please tell everybody
麻烦你告诉大家
you've defeated Master Liu in a duel
你是不是跟碎师傅比武 把他打趴下了
Master Ip-:- You got to clear my name
革师傅 你 你要逮我清白
You liar, why‘re you bothering Brother Ip?
你还在襄谎 还来打摄问哥
I saw the duel when I was picking up my kite
我撩风律时亲眼看见他们比武的
Your kite was cut and fell into Brother Ip‘s house
你的风等就吉床巧遍了入 落在问哥家院子壬
You saw the whole duel between the two masters
你又过愿巧看见碎师傅跟问哥切磋
Isn't that too much of a coincidence?
整个过程又过愿巧被你看网
That's exactly what happened
哪来吉床多巧合啊
Even if it’s true,
就是过厌巧嘛
you shouldn't have told everyone
就算是真的 你也不可以到处去褒
You're not supposed to admit to certain things
有的事情是不能记的
What's wrong with admitting to the truth?
是真的就不怕证
That might cause embarrassment for others
证了很丢及的
What embarrassment? I don't Know so much
丢什么及 我哪知道啊
This is embarrassment !
各就叫丢腔
You don't need to do that, Lin
了武癜林 没必要过样
Why're you laughing? You think I'm invisible?
笑什么笑 没把我党回事啊
Captain... it's no big deal
队长 小事而已
What no big deal?
什友小事
Leave!
散开啦
Don't you leave!
不准走
Captain, it's no big deal
队长 小事
I saw everything. I'm warning you...
我全都看见了 我告诉你们
I‘11 nab whoever that causes trouble on my turf
谁在我李剑的地租搞事 不守规矩
I didn't cause any trouble
我就抓谁
Someone ruined my name.
不是我来挑事 是有贷雯我的专涡
I'm here to claim justice
我是来讨个公道
What justice? I am justice
讨什么公道 我就是公道
You hooligans are fighting all the time
你们过帮老粗 整天动手动脚
What age are we in now?
现在什么年代啦
Still talking about martial arts?
还比武功
We're talking about arms and guns!
比武器啊 检啊 栓啊
Guns. Got it?
知不知道
You Know, Captain Li...
你也知道 李队长
We martial artists are energetic Sometimes we might be a bit too loud
我们和练武之人底气足 有了时候褒话就是大韦
But that doesn’t mean we're not civilized
不过襄话大韦 不代表没有礼貌
We're civilized folks. Please don’t pull the gun
理详上大家都是文明人 不用动不动拔检嘛
Cut me some slack
给个面子
Lin, set a table for Captain Li. It's on me
武闻林 招呼一下李队长 算我的
Yes...
好 好啊
Captain Li. this way please
李队长 吉亡请
What you looking at? Get lost
看什和三看 还不赶快走
Don't look. Don't look... Get out of the way
别看啦 都散了
Please
李队长 请
Master Liu
廖上师傅
As you please
自便了
Why so secretive?
你干路过奈神神秘秘
I'm really not good at business
我真的不通合做生意
Take this to set up the mill. Pay me back if you make a profit
拿去开厂 赚到钱再还和给我
It'1]1 be a while before I can repay you
我汽过床快能逮和给你呀
Take your time
慢慢膛
Another request: take my son as your disciple
再才我一个忙 收我儿子做徒弟
There're so many martial club masters. Ask them
武馆竺有过奈多师傅 找他们教就行了
None of them is better than you
外面的师傅 泊有你过好嘛
We're similar
差不多
Brother Ip
问哥
Lin
了武闻林
Brother Quan
泉哥
I learnt some new moves. Practice with me
问哥 我学了一新招 你才我试试看行不行
You got so much time. You found your brother?
你过友空 找到弟弟汽有
Let him be. He'11 come back once he spent all his money
不用管他 汽钱用了就会回来
Let's try
试一武
Dad. did Uncle Ip agree?
老将 问相肯不肯
Let's go watch over there
你先去看看
You draw very well, Zhun
阿准 你必得真漂亮啊
What new moves have you learnt? Let's see
你又学了什么新招 看看
Brother Ip. my master says
问哥 我师傅襄呢
this move is offense and defense all in one
各一招是攻中有防 防中有攻
Attack while defending. Defend while attacking
攻不刻防 防不喜攻的
Aren't they the same?
你襄的四句都一柑
Go away, ignorant kid
小致子不懂的 走踪一点啊
This move attacks the midrib
过招就是打人中路 非常属害的日字溃槐
Stop reciting mantra. Hit your target
你不要只知道念口扇 最关键要打到人
Mom, I'm done with my drawing
嫂妈 我画好了
So beautiful. Show it to Dad
尾得真好 去拿给爸爸看吧
OK.
好
Hit to disperse. Disperse while hitting
以打况消 违消带打嘛
My last move was “disperse while hitting"...
我是过床做的 刚才那权招就是志消
Dad. look
爸爸 你看
Wait. I'm not free at the moment
区区没空 你等请儿
You don't get it? No
不明白
Come again if you don't get it
是啊 不明白再来
Try again
绸来一次
Dad doesn’t want to see it
爸爸 不看
There you go
你已经输了
What?
什友
That was “disperse while hitting”
过就叫连消带打
Once more, Master Ip I couldn't see clearly
革师傅再打一次 我刚才泡看清
See? What you wanna see?
看看看 看什感看
You guys fight every day. Aren't you tired?
每天都来打打打 烦不烦
You okay. Brother Ip?
问哥 怎友样
Sorry, Mrs Ip
嫂子 不好意思
Goodbye. Mrs Ip
嫂子 我先走了
I wasn't talking about you
我不是襄你呀
No. there're things to take care of at the mill
不是 工厂玩有很多事要做
Yao
阿兆
I gotta go, Uncle Ip
问叔 我先走了
Okay, see you next time
好 下次再来
Bye. Ip
走啦
Talk to me if you're not happy No need to throw a tantrum
你不高旺就跟我说嘛 不需要发脾气
Okay. please take a look at your son's drawing
那好 我就请你看一下儿子书的娃
Spend more time with him instead of your pals
多关心他一下 不要整天只陪著朋友
Let's go inside, okay?
进去吧 好不好
Go
慢点
Brother
兄弟
Where's the martial club street?
武馆街在哪
Ah.
啊
Martial club!
武馆
Go straight ahead
前面直走
One, two...
一 一一
Which martial club should be challenge first. Bro?
大哥 过友多武馆 先打哪家
One... two!
一 一一
One... Back!
一 收
You teach martial arts here?
兄弟 教源啊
Come in if you wanna learn
你们是来拜师的 进来再说
Who's the patriarch?
谁是馆主
I am
我就是馆主
My name is Jin
我叫金山找
I come here as Fo Shan is famous for martial arts
入半佛山是武术之乡 所以专程南下
I'd like to practice with Fo Shan's martial artists
想跟佛山的武师切磋武要 交流心得
Pratice?
切磋武艺
Yes!
针
Provacation rather?
那就是来踢馆子啦
I'm obliged
指教 指教
Okay!
好
Stand aside
你们站一和去
See how I‘11 beat these out-of—towners !
看看你师傅我 是怎厅教训过才乡巴做的
Not here. Stand over there
不是那净 运稳各稳
What about it?
怎奈啦
Wait and see!
学车点
Very good!
大哥 大哥 属害
Where's your master?
你们师傅在哪
Here!
我在过
You wanna hack me to death?
你真想劈死我呀
Our master is not here
师傅不在
Weather is so treacherous in Fo Shan these days
佛山的天所都不知道怎厅了 又病又热的
Let me
我来
What are you drawing, Zhun?
娃什三 阿准
He's ignoring you.
阿准都不理你了
Spend more time with him
有空多陪陪他吧
Okay
好
So early, Lin?
武癜林 过床早
Yes I'm not here to fight.
嫂子 我不是来打架的
Just a few words
讲两句话就走
What's the matter?
苏 什么事
Some out—of—towners are provoking all the clubs
来了一群贿下人 到上处去踢馆
Their kung fu is too good for all the masters
功夫非常属害 家家武馆都栅不住
Can you look into that if you can?
可以的话 去看看
That good?
有那友属害
Yes
是啊
I gotta go. Mrs Ip
嫂子 先走了
Hang in there, Master Liu!
挺住啊 大师傅
We depend on you. Master Liu!
靠你啦 廖师传
Damn it
他奶奶的
No one in Fo Shan Knows martial arts at all
佛山一个能打的都泊有
I thought everyone was Wong Fei-hong here
我以为呀 佛山全是黄飞瀛
It turns out you are just bums
原来是一休曼
You can't even fight. let alone defend yourselves
雕串小技 不塌一遇
Brothers, our efforts have not been wasted
兄弟们 过赵咱汽白来
Nobody in Fo Shan Knows martial arts
佛山一个能打的都泊有
We'll be rich this time
各回 咱们发财啦
Brothers, let's keep it up
兄弟们 我们要继续努力
We open a club here to show them our might
在佛山开武馆 让他们知道咱们的属害
We will be No.1 in Fo Shan!
我们要做佛山第一
You think you're good by beating a few nitwits
你们过攻乡巴侍 打趴友个扬设就是高手了
Wait till you beat the best
打赢最属害那个再襄吧
Who's the best in Fo Shan?
佛山谁最能打
Ip Man, of course!
当然鞠问 亩道我啊
Go!
走
Come with us!
来啊 来啊
See how we shall defeat Ip Man
看我们怎友打赢革半
Dad, there're lots of people outside
区区 外面好多人呀
Sir... they...
少蓄 他们
Are you Ip Man?
你叫革于
I'm Jin. Heard that Fo Shan's famous for kung fu
我叫金山找 久间佛山是武术之乡
I understand, Master Jin. I understand
知道了 金师传 知道了
You bring a crowd here to challenge me to a duel?
你带那友多人来 不就是想告诉我你想切磋了嘛
Of course
那当然了
We're opening a club here to show our might
我们在佛山开武馆 当然要拿点本事玉人看
To open a martial club...
开武馆是吧 开武馆你不用跟我打呀
you need a good site. No need to fight with me Please leave!
你找个好地方不就行了 请你底开
Uncle Wang. take Zhun inside
旺叔 带阿准进去
Ip Man!
革问
Don't dillydally. Are you scared?
你别推三阻四 你是不是怕了不敢打
You think our house is a martial club?
打什三打 你沼我们家是武馆了
Who's going to fight with you? Get lost!
随便你们和进来打打角欠 快和给我滚
You heard that. I won't fight with you
你对昂了 我是不会跟你打的
Please leave immediately
请你马上给我出去
I heard Wing Chun was invented by a woman
我聘襄访春源是个女人齐的源
That suits you just right
我看挺通合你呀
Are you afraid of your wife, Ip?
革问 你还真怕老婆啊
No men are afraid of their wives
各个世上汽有怕老婆的男人
There're only men who respect their wives
只有尊重老婆的男人
Don't worry. Mrs Ip. I won't beat him to death
革太太 你放心 我不会打死他
If you fear he'll] lose. I‘11 use only one hand
你要是怕他输 我驴他单手
If that's not enough, I can use no hands at all
再不行 我太他稳手怎友样
Fight with him, Master Ip! Beat him up!
革师傅 打吧
I'm too disappointed by Fo Shan. Damn it!
佛山 太鞠我失望了
So many martial artists but none of them good
过奈多和练产的 居然洛一个
Shut up!
闭嘴
Don't break my things
别打灶家里的东西
Get out of my way!
让并 让开 对并
You rascals
你们吉帮人
You come at the right time This place is small.
你来得正好 我各个地方有点小
Please get outside and close the door on your way out
麻烦你请乡亲们出去 顺便帮我关上门
You have to redeem our honor
要才我们争口气啊
Ask them to leave. Hurry up!
让他们出去 快
Hurry up! Get out Can I just watch?
快点 快点 出去 出去 出去
Hurry up! Get out!
快走快走
Get out! Get out!
出去出去
Wing Chun, Ip Man
访春 革半
how a man can fight like a woman
你一个大男人 是怎友打出一套女人源
Good kung fu does not depend on age or sex
好的功夫是不分男女老少的
but on how well you fight. You will Know later
那得看人 你马上就知道是怎友打了
Please.
=主 ]
I‘11 pay!
我赔
Good!
好
Dad. Mom said
爸爸 嫂嫂讼
if you don't start fighting everything in the house will be broken
你再不出手的话 家壬的东西就全破啦
Okay
好啊
Little rogue
臭小子
Mind you language
襄衣小心点
Bro...
大哥
You all right. Master Jin?
金师傅 没事吧
I'm fine!
没事
How about that, Master Jin? My kung fu isn't too bad, eh?
怎奈样 金病传 我的功夫膛可以吧
That's enough
不用褒啦
My northern boxing has lost to your southern one
今天北方源输给南方举了
No, it’s not a matter of northern or southern style. The problem is you
你错了 不是南北源的问题 是你的闫题
So who won?
谁奏谁赢了
Look how depressed he is. He must have lost
还用问 看他殖头样 就知道一定输啦
Get lost! Go back to your hometown! Get lost. you out—of—towners!
滚吧
Master !
师傅
Brother Ip!
问哥 革师傅
You fought very well, Ip!
好样的
You've redeemed the honor of our martial clubs
你为我们佛山武馆街出了一口气呀
Don't be modest. You are Canton's treasure!
照我说 你就是我们的魔东之实
Take a look. It's imported
禹是刚从外地进口来的 你随便看看
Master Ip. flowers for your wife Thanks
革先生 过是您太太要的花
How much, boss?
老团 多少钱
On the house, Master Ip
不用钱咬 革上师傅
I can't let you pay. You saved our honor
你为我们佛山人增了光 怎奈能收你钱呢
How can that be?
怎奈可以不用钱了呢
You're running a business Don't stand on ceremonies .
你们做生意嘛 真的不用了 药师传
Okay. next time
下一砍
Fruits, Master Ip You're too kind. I can't
革师傅 拿点水果吧 过奈客气啊
For the kid Thank you
给小到吃嘛 怎感好意思
Please come again. Goodbye
再见 全师传
Buddy Take this
小朋友 拿去玩
Say thank you
不用谢
Farewel]
慢走
How are you. Master Ip? How are you?
革师傅 你好 你好
That isn't bad at all
各个不错啊
Yes, this is the best in our shop
各个是我们店壬最好的一个
It's our honor if it can be placed in your house
如果过个能狗放在你的家壬 是我的光业
Thank you
客氟
What's the occasion?
过奈娄半
Uncle Man. Auntie
问叔 阿姨
You plan on opening a martial club...
你真没意思
why didn't you inform me first?
你要开武馆 为什么不第一时间通知我
When did I say that?
我权时襄要开武馆
Everybody in Fo Shan Knows about it
全佛山都知道了
Everybody in Fo Shan but me
全佛山都知道 我不知道啊
Let me help you, Uncle Man
问叔 我帮你拿
Master. Madam
师传 师母
Bro
师兄
You must be the one spreading the rumor
看来散播族言的一定是你了
Keep order for me
你收拾各个抽子吧
Come. Go yourself
来 自己走
I don't care. Yao has to be your first disciple
我不管 你一定要收阿耀做第一个徒弟
Come on. You've Known me long enough
你又来啦 你又不是第一天认识我
I don't like having disciples
我不收徒弟的嘛
Be quiet
静一静
Stay in order Stay in order and hail
大家要守秩序 守秩序就对了
Master Ip! Master Ip...
革师傅 革师传
On July 7, 1937, the Marco Polo Incident broke out.
一九三七年七月七日 虚潢宛事变爆发 日军大举侵华
In October, 1938, Fo Shan was occupied by the Japanese army
一九三八年十月 佛山渝陷 日军大律破坏请房 设备和楼宇
The population of Fo Shan shrunk from
三十多万人口的佛山
more than 300,000 to just over 70,000.
俊剩七万族人
Only a dozen factories in the whole city remained in operation still.
全市亦仅存十多个作坊炎续生产
Ip's residence was also confiscated and
革家大宅亦遭日军霸估 用作上日军各部
Ip's family was rendered homeless, living an abject existence.
革问一家三口无家可蜗 生活苦困
Cheng, I'11 step out for a sec. Will be right back
永成 我出去一会 很快回来
Wait
等一等
It's cold outside. Wear a jacket
外面天疹 多穿一件
Zhun
革准
Be careful, Zhun. Don't hurt others
革准 小心点 别弄佬人
I‘'11 give you more, Master Ip
革师傅 我多给你一点
Thank you
多谢了
The mill may be old but it's still productive
过语子内然荔点 但做得还不错
Fo Shan is very chaotic these days
佛山现在凯哄哄的
You left already. Why did you come back?
你都走了 还回来
Who's going to feed the workers otherwise?
不回来 各些工人哪有饭吃
All my money is invested in this mill
我的钱全部投在过壬
I can’t pay you back for now
一时还不能有还你
Don't worry. I almost forgot
不用了 你不襄我都不记得吉事了
No. I'11 consider you a shareholder then Let me calculate---
那怎友可以呀 就当你入股
you should have ten percent shares
从然少了一点 也有一成的股份
It's really unnecessary
真的不用了
Stay and help out, now that you own it too
留下来帮我吧 反正请子有你一份
Uncle Ip
问叔
Yao
光耀
You'11 be helping out? That's great!
你来帮忙啊 太好了
Everyone will be lively under your leadership
有你带著我们 大家都傅精神点
And I can watch you practice Wing Chun
还可以看你打访春拳呢
Ip. stay for lunch. It's lunchtime for the workers
阿癌 留下来吃饭吧 工人开马了
Yes, let’s have lunch together
是啊 一起吃饭吧
No, thanks
不用了
I'm not free. Next time
我还有事 咱们下次吧
Goodbye
先走
Dad, why didn't you ask Uncle Ip to stay?
老区 怎友不留住问概
He doesn't like to owe people favors
我太瞳解他了
Dad, you used to practice martial arts, right?
爸爸 你以前不是经常打源吗
Why did you stop?
为什么现在不打了呀
I get hungry when I exercise
爸爸动得多会试的嘛
So I need to exercise less, okay?
所以就少动点 对嘲
Got it.
哦 我知道了
I won't play outside from now on
那以后我也不出去玩了
You'll only stop playing today. Go eat
你只是今天不玩了吧 快吃呀
Hurry up and eat
快点吃
This congee is a bit too thick
过粥是者糊了一些
But you need to eat some
但是你怎菩样都要吃一点
Come on.
来
Be careful it’s hot
小心混
How much rice is left at home?
家壬还有多少米
Don't worry
不用担心啦
I've pawned everything worth pawning
家壬值钱的东西都拿去党了
I am strong.
你老公有和气有力
I can look for a job
我可以出去找活嘛
It's not the end of the world
不会死的
You look for a job?
你出去工作
I didn't need to work.
以前当然不用出去做事
But it's different now There's always a first time
但现在时外不好 凡事都有第一次嘛
We have enough people here We don't need to hire more. Sorry
现在我们各壬的人狗用了 不再请人哟
Boss, are you hiring?
老闫 你过儿逮请不请人
No
不请啦 狗用啦
Thank you
打摄了
You want to hire me, Boss...
老闭 请我吧
You, you, you... Come up here...
你你你上来
Here
你 来
You're looking for a job. Master Ip?
革师傅 你来找工作
Come, come up...
来 来
Thank you
多谢
Brother Ip!
问哥
You can't dress like that to work
问哥 你穿成吉样 干不了活
I didn't expect to pour coals here
我皇友知道要来各儿控煤啊
How are you. Master Ip?
革师傅
How are you?
你好
So many martial club masters here?
怎感那友多武馆的师傅
The boss here used to practice martial arts too
圣呀 过壬的老半以前也学过功夫
That's why he likes to employ martial artists
所以 他很喜静请一些 懂功夫的人来干活
By the way. are you still practicing?
你现在逮和练功吧
I'd rather used my time to scrape a living
有了时间都出来找事做了 是不是
Go that way.
到那示去吃
Okay!
好
I can't finish it all. Help me, okay?
问哥 我吃不下了 攻我吃点 好不好
Eat some
吃点吧
How're your wife and son?
对了 嫂子和阿准他们好吗
They're fine. Thank you
还好 谢谢
Did you find your brother?
怎感样 找到你弟弟没有
I couldn't locate him since he left
上次走了以和俭 就不知道去哪了
Don't Know if he’s still alive
是生是死都不知道
I don't even have the chance to say sorry
想道个舱都没机会
What have you lost?
东西不见了
I lost an iron box
是啊 不昂了个铁盒
What iron box?
什么铁盒
Japanese solders are coming!
有日本兵
Dear workers
日本兵来啦
This is Colonel Sato
各位工友 过是仁和能上校
He appreciates Chinese martial arts
仁艇上校很欣赏中国功夫
He Knows Fo Shan is famous for martial arts
也知道我们佛山是武术之乡
He wants to find Chinese martial artists to fight with the Japanese
想找一些禽功夫的中国人 来跟他们日本人比武切磋
Would anyone want to go?
有没有人里意去
Master?
师傅
You want us to be sandbags?
你想让我们去给他们做沙包
There's no door. I tell you!
我告诉你 没站
Airhead. Whoever that wins will get one sack of rice
余子 打赢了有一包白米呀
Whoever that wins
凡是打赢了的 就赏一包白米
I‘11 go!
我去
Lin... Don't get into trouble
了武闻林 别惹麻烦啦
Me too!
我也去
They took all our rice.
不是啊 他们抢了我们的米
Now I can get them back The world is fair
现在我们有机会拿回来 天经地义嘛
Hey-:-
喂 了虽
Forget it
算了
Help me find the iron box
攻我找回铂盒
Hey-:-
也
Let's go. It's okay. Come
行啦 没事 来
Be careful
中N必台
Come, let's line up
来 过来排队
Come, come, come...
快
Anything else?
还有没有了吟只
No. let's go Yes!
汽有 走 下3 和让
Master?
师傅
General
将军
Good .
好样的 好样的
Got to beat them all
打倒他们
Let me join in the fun
让我也下场玩玩吧
They're not good enough for General Miura
他们不是三蒲将军您的对手
I‘11 show the Chinese what Japanese kung fu's like
就当是攻中国人昂坟一下 我们日本功夫吧
Find three men to fight with me
找三个人来跟我打
Give them rice even if they lose
输给我 同样可以得到白米
Yes, sir!
下3 和让
I've done you a favor again
别襄我不帮你们
General Miura will fight with three of you
我虽 安排了三蒲将军 跟你们三个人打
You can get rice whether you win or not
扰论输赢 都有米途
The rice is not important.
汽米扰所谓
I just wanna beat them
重要的是能打他们
I will...
我去 我去
Let go of me... Stop shouting!
放手 别吵了
Lin, you and you... The three of you
了武闻林 你 你 三个
Okay!
好
You've spit blood. Stop fighting
别 你吐血了 别再打啦
We've lost
我们输了
General. they admitted defeat
将军 他们认输了
Your really wanna die?
迪有此理 你真的那感想死哮
You asshole!
你个混蛋
Lin, how are you? Lin...
武闻林 你怎友样
Lin...
了武问林 武疯林
Were you tired today?
今天累不累呀
Pouring coal is not tiring at all
按煤而已 哪依累啊
I saw Lin today
我今天昂到武闻林了
Really? How is he?
是吗 他怎友样呀最近
Not bad
还好
I didn't expect to see him again
想不到还能碰到他
Master Li, Master Hong
李上师傅 洪师傅
Did you see Lin?
有没有网到武闻林
Lin? No, I didn't
武癜林 没看昂
Let's eat first
先吃马吧
Lots of us received rice yesterday General Miura was very satisfied.
用天好多人拿到米了 三蒲将军很满意
Anybody wants to go today?
今天有没有人想去
Anybody? Li...
有省有人去 李证
Li... Where's Lin?
李剑 武闻林了呢
Anybody wants to go?
有温有人想去
I'm asking you. Where's Lin?
我问你呀 武闻林了呢
I don't Know
我不知道
Of course you do. You took him away
你不知道 是你带他走的呀
Anybody wants to go? You'll get rice if you win
有温有人要去 打赢了就有白米
Me!
我去
If Master Ip is going. I‘11 go too!
革师傅去 我也去
Me too!
我也去
I wanna have a good fight with the Japanese
我也想跟日本人打一场
Anything else I can do?
还有没有了吟只
No, you can go
汽有 快走
Can I fight three more people?
我可不可以再挑战三个
He said he wanted to fight three more people
他襄 他要求再挑战三个
That's it for me...
我不打了
Why did you open fire?
为什么要开榆
Li! Why did you open fire?
李惠 为什感要并榆啊
Who let you open fire?
谁攻你开栓的
He took the rice even though he's lost
我网他输了 渤胸敢取米
so... I wanted to teach him a lesson
所以 才教训他
This place is for tournaments only
各壬只是用来比武
Never open fire here anymore
以后不可以再在过壬开榆
Got it! Please calm down, General Miura
明白 请三蒲将军息怒
I‘11 arrange the next tournament for you
我立刻幸你安排下一场比赛
Continue!
继续
Who else wants to fight?
还有谁想打
Me!
我打
Li! Open the gate!
李剑 开门啊
Master... Open the gate!
师傅 开门
Tell me, was Lin beaten to death?
你告诉我 武癜林是不是过样被打死的
Open the gate
开门
Master...
师傅
Please open the gate
请打开门
I wanna fight ten people!
我要挑战十个
You crazy? Please don't
你疯了 不要运柑
He said he wanted to fight ten people
他襄 他要求挑战十个
Ten?
十个
Yes
下3 和让
Let's see how good he is
我也想看一下
Unit 5!
第五师围
Unit 1, Unit 3, Unit 5 Start!
第一班 第三班 第五班 开始
Be careful
咯V
Stay back!
停手
Come back again
再来吧
He wants you to come back again
他想你再来
I'm not here for the rice
我不是为过些米来的
He said... he would come back
他襄 他会再来
Hey-:-
也
What's your name?
你叫什么名字
He wants to Know your name
他想知道你的名字
I'm just a Chinese
我只不过是个中国人
His name is Ip Man
他叫鞠辕
Be careful in the future I don't Know what Miura might do
你自己以后小心点 我不知道三蒲会做什么
Lackey!
走狗
Their deaths got nothing to do with me.
他们的死关我什么事
I'm just an interpreter I need to scrape a living too!
我只是个翻潜 我不用吃饭啊
I need to scrape a living!
我要吃访的
Scrape a living?
要吃岛
You watch your countrymen get beaten to death. Where's your dignity?
你看著你同胞被人打死 你有没有尊右
I don't have any You do. You have lots of it
我汽有 你有 你有很多啊
If you have the guts, go beat them up!
你行你去打 把他们都打死
Beat as many as you can!
打死十个一百个 打死一干个
I'm an interpreter, not a lackey...
我是一个翻潜 我不是走狗
I'm a Chinese!
我是一个中国人
I'm back
我回来了
Daddy
相 巴巴
You're back?
回来啦
Have you been good?
有没有了话
Yes
有
Good boy
阿准乖
Are you tired today?
今天累不累呀
Go wash your face first
我先去洗个腔
You're so good
你真好
I realize today I'm useless
我发现自己真的很泊用
I can't do anything
什么都做不了
I practiced marital arts before
以前就知道熏功
But so what?
又能怎友样
This world...
过个世界
is minuscule
真的很竹小
I'm so useless
我真是泊用
I don't care what the world is like
我不管外面的世界怎友样
I only Know I‘m very happy now
我只知道 我现在很幸福
As long as you, me, and Zhun...
只要我 和你 还有阿准
can stay together, everything will be okay
一家人不分开 就什么问题都洛有
It's essential for a family to stay together
最重要是一家人在一起
Get off!
下车
Get off! Get off...
下车 下车啊
I am
我是
I just took your goods. You can buy them back
我刚刚护了你的货 现在彭回答你
Is that okay?
有意见哮
I don't have money
我泊钱
Don't beat my dad anymore!
不要打我老区
Wing Chun?
访春呀
Damn it! Wing Chun?
奶奶的 访春
Don't beat him!
不要打他
Do you have money?
有没有钱
I don't
没钱
Do you?
有没有
I‘11 keep beating you till you have!
打到有钱为止
The goods haven't been sold--- I don't have money
质没喜 我根本没钱
Uncle Ip! Uncle Ip...
问叔 问叔
Please save my dad. He's almost beaten to death
快点救我老区 他快被人打死了
What's the matter. Yao?
什么事 光耀
Auntie
阿姨
Let me go see what happens. It's okay
我去看看 没事的
I'm very reasonable
我跟你襄 我各个人很请道理
It's fine if you don't have money now I‘11 give you some time to raise it
你现在洛有钱 行 我给你一点时间筹钱
As for the goods. I‘'11 keep them for now
人质 我先留黄
Master Ip
革师傅
Dad, are you okay?
老区 你没事吧
I'm fine. Go help Uncle Fu
汽事 去攻你福伯
How can I help?
我有什和三可以帮忙
I thought your martial arts were impractical
以前我澳得你熏功夫 不切实际
Now I Know it's very useful
现在才知道吉订有用
I should've learnt some martial arts from you
早知道 跟你学一招半式回来
At least I can defend myself
起码可以撒杷招
Uncle Ip, please stay and teach us martial arts
问叔 不如留下来教我们功夫
so that we can defend ourselves
我们就可以自保 不被别人期负
Master Ip
革师傅
You're such an expert. Please teach us
你那友好的功夫 教教我们嘛
Yes, Master Ip. Please teach us
是呀 药师倩 教教我们吧
I'm a businessman
我是个生意人
I Know nothing other than running a business
除了做生意 我什么都不傅
I can't protect them, but you can
我保护不了他们 但你可以
In peaceful days, it's okay if you refused to teach
以前天下太平 你襄你不想教
But in bad times now, shouldn't you do something?
现在世道不好 你是不是恋做些什么
Teaching martial arts is very costly
我教功夫很博的
You're paying their fees? You owe me again
工人学费你箱呀 你又欠我一笔
Uncle Ip. I'11 be your first disciple
问叔 我要做你第一个徒弟
Dad, I wanna be taller
区区 我还要高一点
Taller?
还要高一点 好
Why hasn't Ip Man come back?
革问为什么泊有再来
I... I don't know...
我 我也不知道
Find him
把他找出来
I don't Know where he is
可我 真的不知道他在哪壬
I don't Know how to find him
你让我上哪儿找呢
How big is Fo Shan? How difficult can it be to find him?
佛山有多大 很将找吗
Fo Shan is indeed very big
佛山 真的挺大的
No...
不要
I really don't Know where he jis...
我真的不知怎样找他
Useless thing! Enough!
你过个
Asshole!
王八蛋
Paper, stone, scissors!
石头 齐刀 布
You lost You colluded?
你们合胸算计我
Hide wel
藏好啦
10, 9, 8. 7, 6--- Zhun
十九八蕊六 阿准
5, 4, 3, 2, 1 That way
五四三二一 快去藏那冰
I'm coming. I'11 find you guys
我来啦 看我先找到谁
Master
师傅
What ‘re you here for?
你来干嘛
Miura wants you to go back and fight him
三蒲想找你回去跟他打
Go away
走
I can't
不行啊
What are you doing?
干嘛
What do you want?
干什么 你想怎友样
How pretty!
好漂亮呀
Shit
精了
Let's go. It's not safe here
走啊 吉壬不安全
Let's go, Cheng
走啊 永成
Li
李证
You're a piece of shit!
你过个魔物
How could you let Ip run away?
怎奈可能让革问跑掉
I'm sorry...
对不起
Even Colonel Sato could not stop him...
就连作熊主任也摘不了他
I've tried my best already... Sorry
我实在 也是无能为力 对不起
Shut up!
广物
Tell them...
傅仿下去
to dig Ip out! This is an order
把某回找出来
Yes, sir
下3 和让
Little Sis
妹妹
Come here::-
来
Brother, eat something
哥 吃东西
How's the master?
师傅怎感柑
Okay. They are all fine
汽事 他们都很好
Master
师傅
Coming
来了
Madam
师母
See if it fits?
你看能不能穿
So are you well adapted here?
怎奈样 住的还性惯叶
Yes
可以
That's good I'11 let you Know when the meal is ready
钴惯就好 吃包的时候我叫你们
Li...
李证
I'm fine
我泡事
I really don't Know what to say
我真不知道该襄什么
Thank you
麻烦你了
It's okay
行啦
We better leave Fo Shan as soon as possible
我们一定要候快克开佛山了
Quan is trying to find a solution for us
清泉在攻我们想办法
Where shall we go?
去哪儿
Hong Kong
去香港
In fact. it doesn't matter where
其实去哪儿都乱所调
I still have some friends in Hong Kong
我在香港有些朋友
If something happens to me...
如果我出了事
What can happen to you?
你会出什么事呀
Nothing will happen to you
你一定不会有事的
Are you tired today?
今天果不果
They are here again! Let's scram!
他们又来了 快跑
They are here! They are here!
他们来啦 快跑
Is the money ready?
鳅 都准备好了叶
We won't give you money!
我们是不会和给你钱的
What did you say?
你襄什么
I'm not afraid of you! You can't bully us!
我不怕你的 我们不是好期负的
You want me to beat you up?
臭小子 还想挨打是吧
Damn it! Whoever dares to resist-:- just beat him up!
他奶奶的 他们谁敢反抗 就给我打
Stop it!
不要再打哟
No wonder they dare to resist They've found a bodyguard
订怪你们敢反抗 原来请了个保镖
You spurned me for opening a club in Fo Shan
我来佛山开武馆 你们就排挤我
And today, you wanna mess with me again?
今天 你又要来管我
You wanna chase me away?
他奶奶的 你非要直移我叶
No one wanna chase you away
没人要赶绝你
Ip. have you ever been hungry every day?
革问 你试遏每天吃不饮饭吗
Everybody is hungry nowadays
如今人人都洛有一顿饮饭吃
The first day I came to Fo Shan, I told myself...
我来佛山的第一天 我襄允
I would never be hungry again
我不要再手记了
I will never be hungry again! Keep beating!
我不会再扭试 给我打
Beat them!
打
Yuan, why you still idling here? Go!
沙胸源 避著干什么 上
Kill them!
上子
Go
上
How can we get near him?
怎奈打
Let's go!
走
Master, you were so good!
师傅好棒
Yuan
沙胸源
Stop there!
你站住
You Know what you're doing?
你知道你在做什生哮
You're robbing the Chinese
你扩中国人的东西啊
I'd rather be the bully than the bullied
和与其任人期负 我宁原去欺负人
I want everyone to be scared of me!
我要所有人都怕我
Your brother asked me to give this---
各是你哥托我交
Don't talk about him!
不要跟我提他
You Know your brother is dead?
你知不知道你哥死了
He's beaten to death by the Japanese
他是被日本人打死
He looked for you everywhere but couldn't find you
你哥始终在到处找你 不过一直找不到你
Everyone needs to choose his own path
每个人要走的路 都是自己导的
Master. That guy told Miura you're at the cotton mil]
那个混蛋找到三蒲 襄你在棉花厂
Don't go back, ok?
你干万不要回去
I gotta go. Remember. don’t go back
我走了 你不要回去 记住
Scram! Hurry up!
快走 快
Where's Ip Man?
革问在那壬
Where's Ip Man? Tell me!
革半在哪壬 褒
Don't say a word
大家干万不要褒话
You, come here
你过来
Where's Ip Man?
革问在哪壬
Tell me!
襄呀 褒 讼
I'm asking you!
问你呀
Hang in there. I‘'11 figure out something
项住 我在想办法了
Speak !
襄呀 褒 讼
Speak! Speak up...
我在过 革半在过
I'm here! I'm Ip Man...
革问在过 革问在过
I'm here... Li!
我在过
Wait! Wait!
李证
Please wait!
等等 请等一等
Li, tell Miura the workers are innocent
李惠 告诉三蒲 跟工人没关保
Ask Miura to release them
你跟他襄 放工人走
I told you not to come back. Why did you?
叫你不要来嘛 你来干什么
Tell him!
襄给他邓
Sato!
仁租
He dares to hit me... Can't we put him to death?
他敢打我 我就不可以共了他嘲
I Know what I'm doing
我自有分十
Li Yes
李证 下3 和让
Since the day you resisted the Japanese army
从你反抗我们皇军开始
you've already been a dead man
你已经是一个死人
But you're talented, you can be useful to us
但我网你身手不俗 是个可用之人
So I‘11 give you one chance to be
所以 我想和给你一个机会
loyal to the Japanese Emperor
效忠日本天皇
Teach our army Chinese kung fu
教我们皇军中国功夫
That way. we might still spare your life
那感 你还有半点生存的权利
He wanted you to teach the Japanese kung fu
他襄他很欣赏你 想让你教日本人学功夫
I won't teach the Japanese
我不禽教日本人
You wanna see me fight?
你那友想看我打
1°11 fight with you
我就跟你打
He said he would think about it
他襄 他会好好考虑做教官的事
He wants to have a duel with General Miura
他渤想与三蒲将军您切磋
Take him away!
带他回去
Quan, take my wife and kid away from Fo Shan
清泉 你带我老婆致子欢开佛山
General, you really wanna fight with Ip?
将军 你真的要跟莱半比武叶
Of course. He's an expert
当然 他是个将得的高手
But he doesn't look like...
但我看他的样子
he wants to teach the Imperial Army
他根本不会当我们皇军的教官
He must have other motives trying to fight with you
他要跟你打 必定是另有所
General, don't fight with him
你就不要跟他打了
Let me simply shoot him dead
蓝脆 让我一榆紫了他吧
He challenges me to a fight because he thinks he's better than me
他自澳比你强 才会挑战你
If I refuse to accept the challenge
如果你不应战
but shoot him instead...
而把他榆久
isn't that the same as admitting defeat?
那跟认输有什么分别
Fighting with a Chinese
将军跟中国人比武
is not just a matter of personal honor for you
输赢就不仅是将军个人的业辱
It has to do with the national honor of our Empire
而是我们大日本帝国的业辱
Are you saying I will lose?
你是褒我会输嘲
I only fear for the worst
我只怕万一
I will win for sure
我一定会赢
I‘'11 let the whole China Know I've won
我还要驻全中国人知道我赢
Yes! I understand!
是 我知道
I want you to teach us instead of killing you
我不欠你要你做教官
because I appreciate your talent
是因为我欣赏你的身手
But I don't think Chinese Kung fu is better than Japanese
但我艾不雇为 中国武本会比日本武术强
We will fight in front of everybody
因为我们禽在所有人面前比武
That's why we need a fair tournament
所以 大家要公平殉技
You invaded our country
你侵略我们的国家
and killed our people
杀害我们的百姓
Stop being hypocritical
收回你的虚仿
Excuse me
失陪
Let go of me! Let me go back! Let go of my mom...
放开我嫂嫂 放开我 鞠我回去
I promised Ip nothing would happen to you
我答应过阿癌 不会让你有事
It's too dangerous to go back
回去太危障
I heard the Japanese are fighting the Chinese
对襄日本人要跟中国人比武
Who's fighting?
谁呀
Ip Man
革问呀
Look. the whole place is sealed up now
你看现在都把过里封起来了
In the past--- I wished he could be with me every day
从前 我希望他每天都陪著我
So I always complained about his practice
所以经常责怪他和练功
Every time he had a duel with someone-:-- I would throw a tantrum
他每一软跟别人比武 我都会发脾氟
I never truly supported him doing what he liked
我从来省有真真正正支持他 做自己喜苑做的事情
Now--- This could be his last duel
现在 可能是他最后一次比武
I fear there won't be another chance
我害怕以后都洛有机会了
Why don't you give me this chance?
为什么你们不给我过个机傅
Why?
为什么
General Miura says--- For the sake of Sino-Japanese cultural exchange,
三蒲将军襄 要加强中日文化交流
he is having a fair tournament with Master Ip today
今天 跟革师傅在吉壬 是公平殉技
to share their Knowledge in a friendly manner,
交流心得 以武会友
and to bring true peace between the two countries
实现中日真和平
Fair tournament? Is it possible?
公平吏技 襄得好颈
That traitor will surely be killed by the Japanese
我看他那汉奸样 早晚被日本人打死
That's right
没错
Here comes Master Ip!
革师傅来了
General Miura talked about a tournament
三蒲将军就跟你谈什和三功夫 请什么比武
But I don't give a damn!
我才不管
Listen up. If you win
你耿清楚 如果你打赢的话
I will kill you
我请立刻开检打死你
Remember this!
记住
Yes!
下3 和让
You better let Miura win later
一会不要打赢三蒲
Or he won't let you live
如果打赢 他例对你不客氟的
It's more important to stay alive
当心自己的性命要紧啊
Although martial arts involves armed forces
武术 内然是一种武装的力量
Chinese martial arts is Confucian in spirit
但是我们中国武术 是包含了儒家的哲理
The virtue of martial arts is benevolence
武德 也就是仁 推已及人
You Japanese will never understand the principle
禹是你们日本人永和踪 都不禽明白的道理
Because you abuse military power
因为你们涂用武力
You turned it into violence to oppress others
将武力沟成暴力 去期压别人
You don't deserve to learn Chinese martial arts
你们不配学我们中国武术
Ip Man refused to be subjugated by the Japanese army
革问拒绝屈服於日军威嘛 范用稳产唤起中国人的转结心
Assisted by his good friend Zhou Qingquan,
负偶的革半在好友周清泉的功助下 成功与妻儿逃亡佛山
On August 15, 1945, Emperor Hirohito of Japan announced
1945年8月15日 日本裕仁天皇宣伤扰休件投降
The Chinese finally won and ended a war that lasted eight long years.
中国人取得腾利 结束了长过八年的抗战
In 1949, the Grandmaster Ip Man settled in Hong Kong.
1949年 某半宗师导居香港 芷在九龙饭店职工纺会开办
He started his first Wing Chun class at Kowloon Hotel's Staff
第一个访春拳术班 开展了宗师人生新的一页
In 1967, Grandmaster Ip Man started the Wing Chun Athletic Association
1967年 革问宗师终完成其晚年最大心愿
to foster the spirit of Wing Chun with a group of like-minded enthusiasts.
创办了访春体育会 集合一滩同门更心发揭 「访春拳
Until now, Wing Chun has become a world renowned branch of Chinese martial arts.
访春拳发展至今 已是世界知名源术
The lineage of Grandmaster Ip Man's disciples has exceeded 2 million people.
革问宗师的徒子徒允 累计已经超过二百万人
There are lots of talented people among his disciples,
访春弟子人才毒出
including the most illustrious action star of all. Bruce Lee.
当中就包括了一代武打巨星 李小龙